<Chapter Label="ch:GenRefl">
<Heading>Groups Generated by Reflections</Heading>

A central notion of this package are <E>reflection groups</E>, which are
by  definition  groups  generated  by  a  finite  number  of  <E>complex
reflections</E>.<P/>

<Index Key="reflection">(complex) reflection</Index>
<Label Name="lab:ComplRefl"/>
Let <M>V</M> be  a vector space over a subfield  <M>K</M> of the complex
numbers. A <E>(complex) reflection</E> is a non-trivial element <M>s \in
GL(V)</M> of finite order whose fixed point set is a hyperplane (here we
use the  slightly non-standard terminology complex  reflection since the
term <E>pseudo-reflection</E> is usually not meant to imply finite order
and we  abuse the  term reflection  which is  usually only  employed for
pseudo-reflections of  order <M>2</M>). Thus  a reflection has  a unique
eigenvalue which is  a root of unity not equal  to <M>1</M>. If <M>K</M>
is  a  subfield  of  the  real numbers  then  a  complex  reflection  is
necessarily  of order  <M>2</M>  and the  non-trivial eigenvalue  equals
<M>-1</M>.<P/>

A group  is called a  <E>reflection group</E> if  it is isomorphic  to a
subgroup of some <M>GL(V)</M> generated by reflections. <P/>

<Section Label="sec:ReflGrpChevie">
<Heading>Reflection Groups as &GAP; Objects</Heading>

In this  &RefGrp; package  we mark  a group as  reflection group  with a
filter <Ref  Filt="CanGeneratingReflections" />. This filter  means that
we  can ask  the group  for a  list of  generating reflections  with the
command <Ref Attr="GeneratingReflections" />. But  note that this has no
further implications.  The group can be  any type of group  which can be
constructed in &GAP;, it is not necessary that the group <Q>knows</Q> an
explicit  reflection representation.  Consequently, there  are only  few
commands available for general reflection groups. <P/>

First, there is a (not  too useful) function <Ref Func="ReflectionGroup"
/>   for   constructing  a  reflection  group,   and   attributes   <Ref
Attr="GeneratingReflections"  />  for  getting the  list  of  generating
reflections and <Ref Attr="NrGeneratingReflections" /> for their number.
With <Ref Attr="Reflections" /> one can get the list of all reflections,
if  this  is  finite.  These   are  the  conjugates  of  the  generating
reflections and their  non-trivial powers. For each  reflection there is
an  associated label  and there  are  commands to  ask for  them and  to
change  them, see  <Ref Attr="LabelsGeneratingReflections"  /> and  <Ref
Oper="ChangeLabelsGeneratingReflections" />. <P/>

Secondly, there is the  important concept of <E>reflection subgroups</E>
in  the   &RefGrp;  package.  These   are  subgroups  of   a  reflection
group  which  are   generated  by  a  subset  of   its  reflections;  in
particular   they  are   again  reflection   groups.  There   are  three
natural  ways  to  specify  a  list  of  reflections:  By  positions  in
the  list  of  all  reflections  of   a  group,  by  labels  or  by  the
corresponding   elements   of   the  group   itself.   Therefore   there
are   three  operations,   <Ref  Oper="ReflectionSubgroupByPositions"/>,
<Ref         Oper="ReflectionSubgroupByLabels"/>        and         <Ref
Oper="ReflectionSubgroupByElements"/>,    for   generating    reflection
subgroups.  Each  reflection  subgroup  also stores  a  reference  to  a
(reflection)  parent  group,  see  <Ref  Oper="ReflectionParent"/>,  and
there   are  operations   which  describe   the  relation   between  the
reflections  of  a   reflection  subgroup  and  its   parent,  see  <Ref
Oper="ReflectionsInclusion"/> and  <Ref Oper="ReflectionsRestriction"/>.
<P/>

In  most  cases reflection  groups  will  carry additional  information.
For  example, there  may  be  an underlying  root  system which  defines
the  reflections  (see  Chapter  <Ref Chap="XXX"/>)  or  the  generating
reflections are a  set of Coxeter generators for the  group (see Chapter
<Ref  Chap="XXX"/>) or  there is  an explicit  reflection representation
of  the groups  available  (see Chapter  <Ref  Chap="XXX"/>). There  are
classifications  of finite  irreducible  complex  reflection groups  and
in  particular  finite  Coxeter  groups. For  groups  which  know  their
isomorphism type with respect to this  classification there are a lot of
data available  in this package  (like the group  order, representatives
and labels for  conjugacy classes, character tables and  much more). See
Chapter <Ref  Chap="XXX"/> for more details  on this. For many  kinds of
such more special  reflection groups there are  also specialized methods
for the creation of reflection subgroups,  these try to transfer as much
information as possible from the reflection parent to the subgroup.<P/>

</Section>

<Section Label="sec:FunReflGen">
<Heading>Functions for General Reflection Groups</Heading>

In this section we describe  the functions for general reflection groups
in detail.<P/>

<#Include Label="CanGeneratingReflections">

<#Include Label="ReflectionGroup">

<#Include Label="GeneratingReflections">

<#Include Label="Reflections">

<#Include Label="LabelsGeneratingReflections">

<#Include Label="ChangeLabelsGeneratingReflections">

<#Include Label="ReflectionSubgroupGeneric">

<#Include Label="ReflectionParent">

<#Include Label="ReflectionsInclusion">

</Section>

</Chapter>


